The deadly irony/ˈaɪrənɪ  讽刺 反语 / of gunpowder, Everybody loves fireworks --
the lights, the colors,
and, of course, the big boom.
But the history of fireworks
isn't all hugs /hʌɡ 拥抱/  and celebrations.
Long before epic /ˈɛpɪk 史诗般的/ fireworks displays,
chemists in China invented the key ingredient /ɪnˈɡriːdɪənt 原料/
that propels /prəˈpɛl 推进；驱使/ those bright lights into the sky.
That invention was what we now call gunpowder.
Our story begins back in ancient/ˈeɪnʃənt/ China
in the mid-ninth century
where early Chinese alchemists /ˈælkəmɪst 炼金术士/
were trying to create a potion /ˈpəʊʃən 药水/ for immortality /ɪmɔːˈtælɪtɪ 不死；永生/.
Instead, what they created was a flammable /ˈflæməbəl 易燃的/  powder
that burned down many of their homes.
They quickly realized that this black powder,
which they called fire medicine,
was precisely /prɪˈsaɪslɪ 精确地/ the opposite /ˈɒpəzɪt 相反的 背道而驰/ of something
that would make you live forever.
In these early days,
the Chinese hadn't yet figured out
how to make the powder explode;
it was simply very flammable /ˈflæməbəl 易燃的/,
and their armies used it
to make flaming arrows
and even a flame thrower /ˈθrəʊə 投掷者/.
But once they figured out the right proportions /prəˈpɔːʃən 比例/
of ingredients /ɪnˈɡriːdɪənt 原料/ to create a blast /blɑːst 爆炸/,
they began using the powder even more,
creating fireworks to keep evil /ˈiːvəl 邪恶/  spirits /ˈspɪrɪt 灵魂/ away
and bombs to defend /dɪˈfɛnd/ themselves
against Mongol/ˈmɒŋɡɒl/ invaders /ɪnˈveɪdə/.
It was these Mongols, most likely,
who spread the invention of gunpowder
across the world.
After fielding Chinese attacks,
they learned how to produce the powder themselves
and brought it with them
on their conquests/ˈkɒnkwest 征服/  in Persia /ˈpɜːʃə 波斯/  and India.
William of Rubruck,
a European ambassador/æmˈbæsədə 大使/ to the Mongols,
was likely responsible for bringing gunpowder
back to Europe around 1254.
From there, engineers and military inventors
created all kinds of destructive weapons.
From bombs to guns to cannons /ˈkænən 大炮/,
gunpowder left its mark on the world
in some pretty terrible ways,
in contrast /ˈkɒntrɑːst 对比/  to the beautiful marks
it can leave in the air.
So, how does black powder propel /prəˈpɛl 推进；驱使/
fireworks into the sky?
You might have seen old Westerns or cartoons /kɑːˈtuːn/
where a trail /treɪl 足迹/ of gunpowder is lit /lɪt light 的过去式/
and it leads to a large and obviously explosive /ɪkˈspləʊsɪv 炸药/  barrel /ˈbærəl 桶/.
Once the fire gets to the barrel,
a large boom occurs.
But why doesn't the trail /treɪl 足迹/ itself explode /ɪkˈspləʊd/?
The reason is that burning the powder
releases energy and gases.
While the trail is burning,
these are easily released into the surrounding air.
But when the gunpowder
is contained within the barrel,
the energy and gases cannot easily escape
and build up until
BOOM!
Firework canisters /ˈkænɪstə 盒子/ provide
a single, upward-facing outlet /ˈaʊtlɛt 排放口 电源插座/
to channel this explosive energy.
The wick /wɪk 灯芯/ ignites /ɪɡˈnaɪt 点燃/ the gunpowder
and the energy takes
the easiest exit from the canister /ˈkænɪstə 盒子/,
launching the firework high into the sky.
The flame then makes its way
through the firework's encasing /in'keisiŋ 罩子; 套子/
and the same reaction occurs
high above our heads.
So, while the Chinese alchemists /ˈælkəmɪst 炼金术士/
never found the compound /ˈkɒmpaʊnd 化合物/ for eternal /ɪˈtɜːnəl 不朽的/ life,
they did find something
that would go on to shape all of civilization,
something that has caused
many tragic /ˈtrædʒɪk 悲惨的/ moments in human history,
and yet still gives us hope
when we look up in celebration
at the colorful night sky.